Guide to the McKeen-Duren Family Papers, 1720-1945 and undated, bulk 1855-1900
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Diaries and Scrapbooks Series, 1804-1906 and undated, (2.5 boxes)
  - Scrapbooks, 1838-1900s
    - Five scrapbooks, 1838-1900s (Box 10)
      A large scrapbook contains a lengthy series of published exchanges from 1838-1840 on slavery, apparently initiated by Silas McKeen, addressing church members in Mississippi. In the same scrapbook there are many published extracts from The Christian Banner written under the pseudonym Jenny Bradford, most likely Philena McKeen. Some travel pieces are signed by Philena, and clearly pertain to travels which are also documented in her diaries in this collection. Many of the writings by Bradford also appear in a Civil War-era newsletter published by the Tract Society of Boston, and these pages are pasted into the same scrapbook. A second large scrapbook, from the 1860s and 1870s, contains a handwritten chronology of military and civil events during the Civil War, and a handwritten transcription of President Lincoln's last inaugural address, March 4, 1865. Other scrapbooks also contain clippings on slavery, the Dred Scott Decision, and events concerning statehood and slavery, as well as many poems, prescriptive anecdotes, temperance pieces, and other writings by the McKeen family and other authors. One scrapbook contains a pasted-in confederate bill for ten cents, issued in Charleston, S.C. in 1861. The latest date in these scrapbooks appears to be 1902.
- Financial Papers Series, 1821-1890 and undated, (2 folders)
  The first of the two folders comprising this series houses a variety of materials, including certificates announcing professional qualifications; reciepts for cemetary bequest, church assessments, contributions to missionary institutions, good and services, society membership, and subscriptions; a calling card from Miss Dix, and a three-page ledger of monies received. The second folder contains three bound volumes: a memorandum of bonds and obligations in the care of Rev. S. McKeen, 1874; an account ledger pertaining to publication of a book by Silas McKeen, 1875; and an account of expenses of Miss Philena McKeen on behalf of Abbot Academy, 1886.
  - Financial materials (Box 10)
- Genealogy Series, 1839-1945 and undated, (5 folders)
  This series contains handwritten accounts and notes pertaining to the ancestry of the McKeen-Duren families and related branches. Printed materials, usually in the form of obituaries and memorials, also appear in the series. Two hand-written bound volumes contain detailed genealogies of the names of Duren, Gould, Prichard, and Freeman.
  - Genealogy files (Box 11)
- Legal Papers Series, 1720-1938 and undated, (2 folders)
  This small group of materials comprises legal documents relating to the McKeen-Duren families beginning from 1720 and continuing into the twentieth century, among which are land grants and deed transfers, wills, writs of indenture/apprenticeship, powers of attorney, inheritance inventories, loan notices, and service contracts.
  - Legal Papers files (Box 11)
- Photographs Series, 1841-1928 and undated, (5 boxes)
  Arranged by type of material into four subseries: Photograph Albums, Cased Images, Oversize Prints, and Photographic Prints.
  - Photograph Albums, 1889, 1895 and undated
    Three albums, almost certainly related to Philena's trips to England, Scotland, Switzerland, and other places. Philena then wrote travel pieces on these experiences, and these writings are pasted into scrapbooks in this collection.
    - Souvenir album, 1895 (M. Duren) (Box 11)
      Documents travels in England, Scotland, and probably Italy.
    - Edinburgh, 1899 (C. M. Duren) (Box 11)
      Contains many loose prints.
    - Album, late 19th century (G. W. Duren) (Box 11)
      Contains many loose prints of artwork and tourist locales in England and Switzerland; the first print in the album is of a seated woman, and is captioned as being taken in TurkeyEnter scope/content note.
  - Cased Images, circa 1841-circa 1860 and undated
    15 ambrotype and 22 daguerreotype portraits of McKeen-Duren family members and friends. Many cases are fragile - please handle with care. Gloves should be used.
    - Ambrotypes (Box 12)
    - Daguerreotypes (Box 13)
  - Oversize Prints, 1883-1895, and undated
    Sixteen interior photographs of different buildings of Abbot Academy, one exterior photograph of "Maple Walk," presumably on the Academy campus, and prints of three different classes of students at the Academy (1893-1895).
    - Student class portraits, 1893, 1894, and 1895 (Box 14)
    - Unidentified (building??), undated (Box 14)
    - Sunset Lodge, undated (Box 14)
    - Draper Hall, undated (Box 14)
    - Smith Hall, undated (Box 14)
    - Maple Walk, undated (Box 14)
  - Photographic Prints, 1862-1928, and undated
    Approximately 160 portraits of individuals, groups, and animals. The majority of these are albumen prints, usually mounted, of members of the McKeen-Duren families, and almost all are captioned with names and dates. Images for each individual are housed in separate folders. Folders also exist for the Deming, Dunlevy, and Grovenor families, for family pets and other animals, and for unidentified individuals, as well as various identified individuals. There are also 38 photographs of Egyptian monuments and archeological sites.
    - Animals and unidentified people, 1899, 1910, and undated [2 postcards] (Box 15)
    - Deming Family (?), 1862 and undated (Box 15)
    - Dunlevy Family, 1876 and undated (Box 15)
    - Grovenor Family, undated (c. 1870?) (Box 15)
    - Jesse Page Family, undated (Box 15)
    - Fanny Duren, 1876, 1877, 1885, 1888-1890, and undated [2 tintypes] (Box 15)
    - Fanny Duren, 1894-1899 and undated [5 cyanotypes] (Box 15)
    - Fanny Duren, 1900, 1904, 1913, 1914, 1921, and undated (Box 15)
    - Mabel Duren, 1874, 1877, 1883, 1887, 1889, 1891-1895, and undated (Box 15)
    - Mabel Duren, 1896-1898 and undated (Box 15)
    - Alice Serena Duren and Charles and James Duren, 1873, 1874, and undated (Box 15)
    - Gertrude Eliza Whiting Duren, 1871, 1882, 1887, 1894, 1913, and undated [3 tintypes] (Box 15)
    - Charles McKeen Duren, 1887, 1888, and undated (Box 15)
    - Charles McKeen Duren, 1896, 1901, 1920, 1928, and undated (Box 15)
    - Phebe Fuller McKeen, undated (Box 15)
    - Serena McKeen Duren, Charles Duren, and Lizzie Duren, 1850, 1862, and undated [1 tintype] (Box 15)
    - Silas McKeen and Philena McKeen, 1877 and undated (Box 15)
    - William G. Duren, Emma Duren, and Mary F. Duren, 1869, 1873, 1874, 1898, 1899, 1908, and undated (Box 15)
    - Elnathan Freeman Duren, Anna Butler Duren, and Freeman Hyde Duren, 1863, 1869, 1897, 1898, and undated (Box 15)
    - Various individuals, identified, 1857, 1868, 1881, and undated (Box 15)
    - Egypt, undated (Box 15)
- Printed Material Series, 1839-1894 and undated, (3 folders)
  First folder contains an assortment of printed materials, including invitations, event programs, announcements, obituaries and memorial pieces, short story reprints, course curricula, the Abbot Academy journal (including an obituary for Phebe Fuller McKeen), a boarding house business card, and a list of saloon passengers on a 1889 steamship passage. A single folder of newspaper clippings (1859-1882) comprises obituaries, historical pieces focusing on individuals or groups of people; contains a number of travel, local interest, and other short articles written by Phebe or Philena McKeen, sometimes under a pseudonym. The ephemera folder contains a variety of materials (1839, 1884-1898) including a certificate announcing completion of study at the Theological Seminary, Bangor, Maine, by Charles Duren; a receipt for a framed portrait of Phebe; a list of letters sent to Europe; a number of wedding announcements and calling cards; a list of household items with names penciled next to them; and a sketch of the road from Bradford to Vershire, Vermont, annotated with traveling directions, "for Philena and Phebe, 1865."
  - Printed material, clippings, and ephemera folders (Box 16)
- Writings Series, 1816-1899 and undated, (14 folders)
  The Writings Series is divided into two subseries, Manuscripts and Volumes. Manuscript folders of this series (10 folders) contain handwritten copies of short stories and essays, manuscripts, burial services, sermons, speeches, reports, themes for pedagogical purposes, in rough chronological order ranging from 1816 to 1899, with two folders of undated materials. Volumes in the series (5 volumes in 4 folders) contain unattributed handwritten drafts and notes on fictional pieces, essays or texts, most likely written by Phebe. The author of the manuscript sermons is most probably Silas. There may be material in this series related to Silas' anti-slavery writings published in book form and in periodicals prior to the Civil War.
  - Writings files (Box 16)
- Oversize Material, 1833-1857, (1 folder)
  - Diplomas (Box Sec. A OV4)
    - George W. McKeen, Dartmouth (1847) (Box Sec. A OV4)
    - Carol Duren, MA, Bowdoin, Maine (1841) (Box Sec. A OV4)
    - Marianne McKeen, South Berwick Female Seminary (1835) (Box Sec. A OV4)
    - Carol Duren, BA, Bowdoin, Maine (1833) (Box Sec. A OV4)
    - Catherine McKeen, MA, Harrodsburg Female College (1852) (Box Sec. A OV4)
  - Genealogy (Box Sec. A OV4)
    Family tree "For Charles Duren," pen and ink. Tag says Eldora, Iowa, 1934 but signed by artist Dec. 1857.